Stand aside. you. Make way.
Clear a path.
Come on. get back. Out of the way!
I need another oarsman
for my barge. a strong slave.
- Your word is our will.
- The large one there.
You!
No. not that one.
The very dirty one there.
Yes. that one.
He may serve my purpose.
You!
YOU!
Out of the pit!
Out of the way! Back to work!
Clear a path!
Back to work!
First friend of the Pharaoh.
keeper of the royal seal.
Prince of Memphis.
Prince of Thebes.
beloved of the Nile god.
conqueror of Ethiopia.
general of generals.
commander of the Egyptian Host.
and man of mud!
Is that what you want? To be a slave?
Then why aren't you kneeling
at the feet of a princess?
I'm afraid the mud pits have
stiffened my knees. royal one.
Shall I call back the guards?
- Do you think they could bend them?
- Oh. Moses! Moses!
You stubborn. splendid.
adorable fool.
I'm not kneeling to a princess.
No. You are kneeling to a woman
who's been worried about you
day and night since you disappeared.
What is there in the mud pits
that could keep you from my arms?
My people.
Do you have to wallow
with your people? Smell like them?
If they are stained.
it's with the mud of slavery.
If they reek.
it's with the stench of injustice.
- Come back to the palace.
- And hide the truth from Sethi?
That I am Hebrew and a slave.
The truth would break
his dear old heart
and send Bithiah
into exile or death.
Stop hearing the cries
of your people.
Their god does not hear their cry.
Will Rameses hear it
if he is Pharaoh?
No. He would grind them
into the clay they mould.
double their labours.
What about me?
Think of me as his wife.
Do you want to see me
in Rameses' arms?
No.
Then come back with me.
Oh. Moses! The gods have
fashioned you for greatness.
The splendour of your name
will last beyond the pyramids.
As Pharaoh. you can free your people.
worship whatever gods you please.
so long as I can worship you.
I will come to you at the palace
on the day of Sethi's jubilee.
Come with me now.
No. my love.
First I have a call to make
on the master builder.
No. no. no. no. no.
Not red with the samil gown.
My eyes can best be used
elsewhere. Lord Baka.
Before you go. let them look
upon what you thought unworthy.
Who would let beauty
such as this go unseen?
Who would let such a flower
go ungathered?
Dathan. you can see only mud.
so pick up her muddy clothes and go.
Go. all of you.
Did you know that this golden web was
spun from the beards of shellfish?
- Please let me go to my home.
- You ARE at home.
Here. taste this.
The blood of Thracian grapes.
the wine of love.
No wine can change my love.
Then your love shall be my wine.
There's fire in the chariot house!
The chariot house.
Guards! Guards!
Take water to the roof.
Dathan. take charge.
Guards. after him.
Pull it out of the shed.
Take it clear of the house.
No. your wings must not be singed.
at least not by that fire.
- Joshua!
- Run! The way is clear.
The master builder will not follow.
Neither will you. stonecutter.
Bind him between the columns.
See that his arms
are tightly stretched.
You will die on your feet.
stonecutter.
Now go after the girl.
And don't come back without her.
You foolish. stupid man!
I would have kept her
only a short while.
She would have returned to you -
shall we say - more worthy.
Now to whom shall I return Lilia?
You will not be there. Joshua.
You've seen me drive my chariot.
I can flick a fly from my horse's ear
without breaking his stride.
You've seen me use my whip.
You make no outcry. Joshua.
But you will.
You will cry for the mercy of death.
One day you will listen
to the cry of slaves.
This is not that day. Joshua.
You hold your tongue almost
as well as I hold my temper.
It's a pity to kill
so strong a stonecutter.
- Death will bring death. Baka.
- Who are you?
One who asks
what right you have to kill.
The right of a master
to kill any slave.
- Kill ME. master butcher!
- Moses!
Why have you done this?
- Where is Lilia?
- Gone.
Why are you dressed as a slave?
Why does a prince of Egypt kill
the master builder to save a Hebrew?
I am Hebrew.
God of Abraham.
Four hundred years we've waited.
The Pharaoh's soldiers
won't wait so long.
The Almighty has heard our cries.
You are the chosen one.
- I know nothing of your god.
- He knows YOU.
He has brought you to us.
You cannot turn your back upon us.
You will deliver us. The finger
of God points the way to YOU.
- Where was his body found?
- Buried in the sand. royal one.
This is Baka's knife.
There was no wound on the body.
Baka was a powerful man. It would
take strong hands to break him.
The slave. Joshua. is a stonecutter.
Go find me this Joshua.
Joshua's strength didn't kill
the master builder.
Now speaks the rat
that would be my ears.
Too many ears tie a rat's tongue.
Go. All of you.
Well? Who killed him?
I am a poor man. generous one.
What I bring is worth much.
I have paid you much
and you have brought nothing.
Now I bring the world...
true son of Pharaoh.
You offer me the world when you
cannot even bring me the deliverer.
Who killed Baka?
- The deliverer.
- Would you play at words with me?
No. lord prince.
This murderer has now fled
to some distant land?
No. lord prince.
Name him!
One who made himself
a prince and judge over us.
If he knew I were here.
he would kill me.
I will hang you myself
if you tire me further.
There are those who would pay much
for what my eyes have seen.
You haggle with me
like in a marketplace?
No. I will not haggle.
Here's your money.
But for ten talents of fine gold.
I'll give you the wealth of Egypt.
Give me my freedom
and I'll give you the sceptre.
Give me Lilia and I'll give you
the princess of your heart's desire.
Give me this house
and I'll give you the throne.
Give me all that I ask...
or give me leave to go.
I will give you more
than leave to go.
I will send you where you belong.
I belong in your service.
glorious one.
Very well.
I WILL bargain with you.
If what you say pleases me.
I will give you your price.
If not. I will give you
the point of this blade! Agreed?
Agreed.
The deliverer...
is Moses.
Draw one more breath to tell me why
Moses or any other Egyptian
would deliver the Hebrews?
Moses is not Egyptian.
He's Hebrew.
The son of slaves.
I will pay your price.
I am told. my tiger lily.
they're wagering against me.
- Two golden deber against one.
- Yes. I wagered five myself!
You'll lose if Moses
keeps me waiting any longer.
I double the wager. I'll watch
for Moses. you watch the dance!
While you wait to honour Moses.
I will honour Sethi's jubilee...
with a gift.
Strange gift.
You said if the deliverer
were a myth.
- to bring him in a bottle.
- It is empty.
Yes. Because he is not a myth.
- You have found such a man?
- Yes. Father.
In the midst of treachery
and treason.
with the blood of your
master builder on his hands.
Shall I summon him
to Pharaoh's justice?
Summon him!
- Bring the Hebrew in.
Great Pharaoh.
I stand in the shadow
of your justice.
Whose work is THIS?
I warned you of his treason.
- Treason?
- Judge now if I spoke truly.
The evil star foretold him
as the destroyer of Egypt
and deliverer of slaves.
It is not possible.
A prince of Egypt!
He is not a prince of Egypt.
He is not the son of your sister.
He is the son of Hebrew slaves.
Speak...
my son.
I am the son of Amram and Yochabel.
Hebrew slaves.
My brother. it was I
who deceived you. not Moses.
- He was only a child.
- Leave me.
I shall not see your face again.
Come to me.
I do not care who you are
or what you are.
but...
I want to hear from your own lips
that you are not a traitor.
that you would not lead these people
in revolt against me.
Tell me. Moses. I will believe you.
I am not this deliverer you fear.
It would take more than a man
to lead the slaves from bondage.
It would take a god.
But if I COULD free them.
I would.
What has turned you against me?
From the time my sister brought you
to the court. I loved you.
reared you.
set you before my own son.
because I saw in you...
a worth and a greatness
above other men.
No son could have
more love for you than I.
Then why are you forcing me
to destroy you?
What evil has done THIS to you?
The evil that men should turn their
brothers into beasts of burden.
to slave and suffer in dumb anguish.
to be stripped of spirit
and hope and faith.
only because they're
of another race. another creed.
If there IS a God.
he did not mean this to be so.
What I have done.
I was compelled to do.
So be it.
What I do now...
I am compelled to do.
No! No!
Rameses...
Egypt shall be yours.
Hear what I say. Rameses.
When I cross the river of death.
you will be Pharaoh in Egypt.
Harden yourself against subordinates.
Put no faith in a brother.
Have no friend.
Trust no woman.
I protected the helpless.
I nourished the orphan.
Great one!
He who ate my bread
and called me Father...
would make rebellion against me.
What manner of death
do you decree for him?
I cannot speak it.
Let it be as you will.
I will not live if you must die!
The feet of a Hebrew slave
is not the right place
for the next queen of Egypt.
Take him away.
Do not look upon the traitor.
Let the name of Moses be stricken
from every book and tablet.
Stricken from all pylons
and obelisks.
Stricken from
every monument of Egypt.
Let the name of...Moses...
be unheard and unspoken...
erased from the memory of men...
for all time.
No. Moses.
It is I who will possess all of her.
You think when you are in my arms
it will be HIS face you will see?
Yes. Only his face.
I defeated you in life. You shall
not defeat me by your death.
The dead are not scorched
in the desert of desire.
They do not suffer
from the thirst of passion
or stagger towards
some mirage of lost love.
But you. Hebrew.
will suffer all these things...
- by living.
- You will let him live!
I will not make him a martyr.
No phantom will come between us
in the night.
Yes. my sweet. I will let him live.
Dead...
you alone would possess him.
From where I send him
there is no returning.
And you will never know
if he has found forgetfulness
within another woman's arms.
Now. look upon each other
for the last time.
Now look for the first time.
Abiram. upon the governor of Goshen.
Dathan. my brother.
you have the favour of the Lord.
I prefer the gratitude
of the prince.
Nearer.
Yes. Very lovely.
Not that purplish flower.
The purity of white...
will cool the blush of your cheek.
Leave us. All of you.
You. too. my brother.
Continue your playing...
but in the house.
Yes. That's better.
A flower behind a flower.
Dathan. if you fear God. let me go.
I'm here. girl.
because I put no trust
in a desert god
and his mud-pit prophet.
I prospered because I bowed low
before the Egyptians.
Now the Egyptians bow low before me.
Joshua wanted you.
Baka wanted you.
But you belong to ME.
A gift from Rameses
to His Excellency.
I will bow before you. Dathan.
I will work my hands raw for you.
But please...
please do not shame me
before my Lord.
Your Lord is the governor of Goshen.
What difference to my shame?
No difference to you.
But to a condemned slave
like Joshua...
it could make the difference
between death on the spikes
and life in
the copper mines of Sinai.
What would you do to influence
His Excellency's clemency?
Anything. Dathan.
Anything.
Joshua will always
be grateful to you...
my little mud flower.
His fate is better
than the one that waits for Moses.
The slave who would be king.
Captain. Robe of state.
His Hebrew mother brought it
to the prison before she died.
I'd rather this for your armour.
You will have need of a sceptre.
Give me this binding pole.
Here is your king's sceptre
and here is your kingdom...
with the scorpion. the cobra
and the lizard for subjects.
Free THEM. if you will.
Leave the Hebrews to me.
Give this prince of Israel
one day's ration of bread and water.
It will take many days to cross this
wilderness. if he can cross at all.
I commend you to your Hebrew god
who has no name.
If you die. it will be
by his hand. not by mine.
Farewell. my one-time brother.
Into the blistering wilderness.
the man who walked
with kings now walks alone.
Torn from the pinnacle
of royal power.
stripped of all rank
and earthly wealth.
a forsaken man
without a country. without a hope.
His soul in turmoil.
like the hot winds and raging sands
that lash him with the fury
of a taskmaster's whip.
He is driven forward. always forward
by a god unknown
toward a land unseen.
Into the molten wilderness of sin.
where granite sentinels
stand as towers of living death
to bar his way.
Each night brings the black
embrace of loneliness.
In the mocking whisper of the wind
he hears the echoing voices
of the dark.
His tortured mind wondering if they
call the memory of past triumphs
or wail foreboding
of disasters yet to come...
or whether the desert's hot breath
has melted his reason into madness.
He cannot cool the burning kiss
of thirst upon his lips.
nor shade the scorching fury
of the sun.
All about is desolation.
He can neither bless nor curse
the power that moves him.
for he does not know
from where it comes.
Learning that it can be more
terrible to live than to die.
he is driven onward through
the burning crucible of desert.
where holy men and prophets
are cleansed and purged
for God's great purpose.
Until. at last.
at the end of human strength.
beaten into the dust
from which he came.
the metal is ready
for the Maker's hand.
And he found strength
from a fruit-laden palm tree
and life-giving water.
flowing from the well of Midian.
- If only sheep were men!
- Unmarried men!
- Can you think of nothing else?
- I don't know. I've never tried!
You needn't have painted your nails.
There isn't a man from here to Horeb.
- What do you see. Sephora?
- What are you looking at?
- A man.
- What?
- Only one?
- Is he handsome?
- Look at his sandals!
- Egyptian!
- His robe is not Egyptian.
- Who cares?
- He's eaten a whole bunch of dates!
- Could it be dangerous?
- Are you sure he's alive?
- I hope so!
Look. There's REAL trouble.
Amalekites.
- I'll talk to them.
- Talk? Get stones!
- We drew this water!
- Out of the way. girl!
This is the well of Jethro.
our father. You have no right here!
Our goats don't know your father!
- Jethro's mark is on the well.
- They can't read!
Nor can we!
- He's the Sheik of Midian!
- Then let him breed sons!
Let them be first
whose hands have drawn the water.
The stranger is wise...and strong.
Drive back your goats
until the sheep are watered.
We should draw water for YOU
and wash the dust from your feet.
Let me first remove his sandals!
Never did a lost sheep
have so many shepherds.
- We have no towel.
- My veil will serve.
Let me pour the water!
- Am I to be bathed or drowned?
- I'll hold it!
Is it true that Egyptian girls
paint their eyes?
Yes. But very few have eyes
as beautiful as yours.
And who...? Who is the brave one
who stood against the Amalekites?
That's Sephora. She's the oldest.
Since you have already
divided the stranger among you.
I will ask a welcome for him.
- Our father is Jethro.
- He's Sheik of Midian.
Strength to you. stranger.
I am Moses.
Son of Amram and Yochabel.
Health. prosperity. life to you.
Jethro of Midian.
Sephora has told me
of your kindness.
Let us break bread
while she brings meat.
You have come far.
- From Egypt.
- Across the desert? On foot?
He who has no name
surely guided your steps.
No name? You Bedouins
know the god of Abraham?
Abraham is the father
of many nations.
We are the children of lshmael.
his first-born.
We are the obedient of God.
My people look to him
for deliverance.
But they are still in bondage.
Tomorrow we go to the high pastures
beneath God's holy mountain.
My tent would be favoured
if you joined us.
I am a stranger in a strange land.
I have no wealth.
no skill as a shepherd.
And it is...death to give
sanctuary to a runaway slave.
Slave?
Not among our people. You have
wisdom. You need nothing more.
And there are seven to teach you
the tasks of a shepherd.
- Sephora is the eldest.
- You can learn best from her.
I will dwell in this land.
- Today he sleeps.
- Who sleeps?
He who has no name.
Did God live on this mountain?
Sinai is his high place. His temple.
If this god IS God.
he would live on every mountain.
in every valley.
He would not be only the god
of Israel or of lshmael alone.
but of ALL men.
It is said he created all men
in his image.
And he would dwell in every heart.
in every mind...
in every soul.
I do not know about such things.
But I DO know that the mountain
rumbles when God is there.
And the earth trembles
and the cloud is red with fire.
At such a time. has any man ever
gone to see him face to face?
No man has ever set foot
on the forbidden slopes of Sinai.
Why do you want to see him. Moses?
To know that he is.
And if he is. to know why
he has not heard the cries of slaves.
Moses. it would be death
to look upon his face.
How many of my people have died
because he turned away his face?
Can a man judge God?
No. Moses.
We cannot see his whole purpose.
Even lshmael did not know that God
drove him into the desert
to be the father of a nation.
Is it not enough to know that he has
saved you from the Pharaoh's anger?
How do you know that?
You walk like a prince.
And you fight like a warrior.
There is word in the caravans
of a great one
who was driven out of Egypt.
This is not the sceptre
of a prince...
but the staff of a wanderer.
Then rest from wandering.
My father has many flocks
and no son to tend them.
There would be peace of spirit
for you. Moses.
in our tents
beneath the holy mountain.
You have strong faith in this God.
But. for me.
there is no peace of spirit
until I hear the word of God...
from God himself.
I wish every day
was a shearing festival!
And all the men following you
like sheep to be sheared!
- One would be enough!
- If he were Moses!
Never before has our wool
brought so rich a payment.
Moses has sold the whole shearing
of all the tribes in one piece.
His words are truth.
His trading is just.
Peace be with you. sheiks of Sinai.
Why are you dressed like that?
Aren't you dancing with us
before the sheiks?
No. I am not going to dance
before the sheiks. Here.
And I am not going to be displayed
like a caravan's wares
before Moses or any other man.
Tonight I tend the sheep.
You needn't laugh.
Moses may not choose YOU either!
Moses shall no longer
be a stranger among us.
- Give him of our flocks.
- And let him choose.
I shall give him choice
of my seven daughters for wife.
The shadow of my wisdom has fled.
Can a man choose
from among the stars of the sky?
Consider them as they dance.
Cohab. strike a bow.
- A pleasant task.
- Indeed!
A bride. a shawl.
Choose one. not all.
One shawl. one wife.
Your choice for life.
One is a great price.
- Which. Moses?
- Which will it be?
Make your choice. Moses.
It is a garden of many flowers.
I wish you had my years
and I had your choice.
In the tent of Jethro
there is dignity. honour. freedom...
and beauty.
All that a man could ask of life.
But my heart is still
a prisoner of the past.
I...I cannot choose now.
- Strength to you. sheiks of Sinai.
- May God guide your heart.
Moses...!
Tonight he is awake.
Which of my sisters did you choose?
I made no choice. Sephora.
She was very beautiful. wasn't she?
This woman of Egypt
who left her scar upon your heart.
Whose skin was white as curd.
Her eyes.
green as the cedars of Lebanon.
Her lips. tamarisk honey.
Like the breast of a dove.
her arms were soft.
And the wine of desire
was in her veins.
Yes. She was beautiful...
as a jewel.
A jewel has brilliant fire...
but gives no warmth.
Our hands are not so soft
but they can serve.
Our bodies not so white.
but they are strong.
Our lips are not perfumed...
but they speak the truth.
Love is not an art to us.
It's life to us.
We are not dressed
in gold and fine linen.
Strength and honour are our clothing.
Our tents are not
the columned halls of Egypt...
but our children
play happily before them.
We can offer you little...
but we offer all we have.
I have not little. Sephora.
I have nothing.
Nothing from some
is more than gold from others.
You would fill
the emptiness of my heart.
I could never fill all of it. Moses.
But I shall not
be jealous of a memory.
May the gods bless you
as you go to join them
in the land of the dead.
The old windbag.
What an infernal fuss.
After all.
dying is only a part of living.
You won't die. old crocodile.
You'll cheat death the way
you cheat me at hounds and jackals.
I'm afraid he won't let me cheat
the way you do.
You'll be Pharaoh by sunset. Rameses.
I hope you're content...at last.
I am content to be your son.
You have restored Egypt
to her greatness.
I shall make her greatness
feared among nations.
No doubt. no doubt.
You can overcome anything...
but your own arrogance.
Don't exhaust yourself. great one.
Dear great one.
Why not. kitten?
You are the only thing
I regret leaving.
You have been my joy.
And you. my only love.
Uh-huh.
Now YOU'RE cheating.
- There was another.
- Yes.
I know.
I loved him. too.
With my last breath.
I'll break my own law
and speak the name of...
Moses.
The royal falcon
has flown into the sun.
Did the little boy die in the desert.
my father?
No. God brought lshmael and
his mother. Hagar. to a good land.
The same God who lives
on the mountain?
It may be. my son.
Your mother is calling.
Here!
Moses!
There is a man among the sheep!
You stay...
Keep sounding the alarm.
Stay here till your mother comes.
In the cleft. behind the rock.
Your eyes are sharp
as well as beautiful.
Tokar!
Setaft! Back!
Setaft. back!
Come down!
Down. Tokar!
Praise God I have found you!
Joshua?
We thought you dead.
In the copper mines.
the living ARE dead.
Sephora! Bring water.
How did you find me?
A merchant buying copper
saw you in the tent of Jethro.
Here. you too will find peace.
Peace?
How can you find peace or want it.
when Rameses builds cities mortared
with the blood of our people?
You must lead them out of Egypt!
God made a covenant with Abraham
that HE would deliver the people.
Am I the hand of God?
- Sephora. give him water.
- Water! Bless you!
The desert sun
has set fire to his mind.
His name is Joshua.
I once killed that he might live.
They said you were condemned
but I knew you were chosen
to take the sword of God
into your hand!
I am not the man.
I am a shepherd with flocks...
That light on the mountainside...
Do you see that strange fire?
- A bush that burns?
- No.
It is on fire
but the bush does not burn.
Sephora. take him.
Serve him food in our tent.
I will turn aside
and see this great sight.
I am here.
Put off thy shoes from off thy feet.
For the place whereon thou standest
is holy ground.
I am the God of thy father.
The God of Abraham.
the God of lsaac
and the God of Jacob.
Lord...
Lord. why do you not hear the cries
of their children
in the bondage of Egypt?
I have surely seen the affliction
of my people which are in Egypt.
And I have heard their cry
by reason of their taskmasters.
For I know their sorrows.
Therefore. I will send thee.
Moses. unto Pharaoh.
that thou mayest bring my people
out of Egypt.
Who am l. Lord.
that you should send me?
How can I lead this people
out of bondage?
What words can I speak
that they will heed?
I will teach thee what thou wilt say.
When thou hast brought forth
the people.
they shall serve me
upon this mountain.
I will put my laws into their hearts.
And in their minds will I write them.
Now. therefore. go.
And I will be with thee.
But if I say to your children
that the God of their fathers
has sent me.
they will ask. "What is his name?"
And how shall I answer them?
I am that I am.
Thou shalt say.
"I AM hath sent me on to you.
Is the holy mountain
forbidden to men?
Yes. And I am afraid for him.
Then he is more than man. for look...
Look at his face.
He has seen God.
Moses...your hair...your sandals.
I stood upon holy ground.
Can you tell us. Moses?
My eyes could not look upon him.
Did he speak?
He revealed his word to my mind.
And the word was God.
Did he speak as a man?
He is not flesh but spirit.
The light of eternal mind.
And I know that his light
is in every man.
Did he ask something of you?
That I go to Egypt.
You ARE God's messenger!
He has set the day of deliverance.
I will get water and bread
that we may leave at once.
But Egypt holds death for you.
If it be his will.
Where he sends you. I shall go.
Your God is my God.
I will lead men against the armoury
and get swords!
It is not by the sword
that he will deliver his people.
but by the staff of a shepherd.
And the Lord said unto Moses.
"Go. Return into Egypt."
And Moses took his wife and his son
and he returned to the land of Egypt.
And Moses took the rod of God
in his hand.
Let the ambassador from Priam.
king of Troy. approach the Pharaoh.
Great Pharaoh. the gift of Troy
is a fabulous fabric
from the land of the five rivers.
Our thanks to Priam.
It is fabulous indeed.
- It shimmers like the Nile.
- How is it made?
No one knows.
It is spun on the looms of the gods.
They call it silk.
The ambassador from Jericho.
What kingdom has sent you?
The kingdom of the Most High.
- What gifts do you bring?
- We bring you the word of God.
What is this word?
Thus sayeth the Lord God of Israel.
"Let my people go!"
The slaves are mine.
Their lives are mine.
All that they own is mine.
I do not know your God.
nor will I let Israel go.
Who are you to make their lives
bitter in bondage?
Men shall be ruled by law.
not the will of other men.
Who is this God
that I should let your people go?
Aaron.
Cast down my staff before Pharaoh
that he may see the power of God.
In this you shall know
that the Lord is God.
Mother! He turned his staff
into a cobra!
Nothing of HIS will harm you. my son.
The power of your God
is a cheap magician's trick.
Jannes.
Mother. look!
Jannes. do you see?
Moses' serpent
swallows up the others.
You gave me this staff
to rule over scorpions and serpents.
but God made it a rod
to rule over kings.
Hear his word. Rameses. and obey.
Obey?
Are there no magicians in Egypt
that you have come back
to make serpents out of sticks?
Or cause rabbits to appear?
I will give your staff
a greater wonder to perform.
Bear it before your idle people
and bid them make bricks
without straw.
- How can that be done?
- Let his staff provide them.
Or let them glean straw
for themselves.
But their tally of bricks
shall not diminish.
So let it be written.
So let it be done.
Aaron. Aaron. when do we leave Egypt?
We do not leave Egypt.
But Moses promised us.
But you said we'd be freed!
I have brought more evil upon you.
God forgive my weak use
of his strength.
Moses. what have you done to us?
It is Pharaoh's order
that you be given no straw
to make your tally of bricks.
No straw?
How can we make bricks without straw?
You will glean the fields by night.
Your women and children. too.
Is this the deliverer?
You've brought
the wrath of Pharaoh upon us!
You put a sword in their hands!
Stone him! Stone him!
Stand aside! Come!
Follow!
There goes your deliverer.
Now go find your straw.
Remember the tally must be the same.
Not one brick less.
I cursed you.
Each time Rameses took me
in his arms I cursed you. not him.
because I love you.
The Moses who loved you
was another man.
No. he was not.
You believe you've changed.
but you haven't.
You call yourself a prophet.
a man of God.
but I know better.
I don't believe only the thunder
of a mountain stirs your heart.
as you stir mine.
Nefretiri. I have stood in the
burning light of God's own presence.
It was not he who saved you just now.
I did that.
Oh. Moses. Moses.
Why. of all men. did I fall in love
with the prince of fools?
But I believe anything you tell me
when I'm in your arms.
Why must you deny me and yourself?
Because I am bound to a God
and to a people
and to a shepherd girl.
A shepherd girl?
What can she be to you?
Unless the desert sun
has dulled your senses.
Does she...grate garlic on her skin?
Or is it soft as mine?
Are her lips chafed and dry
as the desert sand?
Or are they moist and red
like a pomegranate?
Is it the fragrance of myrrh
that scents her hair?
Or is it the odour of sheep?
There is a beauty beyond the senses.
Nefretiri.
Beauty like the quiet
of green valleys and still waters.
Beauty whose spirit
you cannot understand.
Perhaps not.
But beauty of the spirit
will not free your people. Moses.
YOU will come to me
or THEY will never leave Egypt.
The fate of Israel
is not in your hands. Nefretiri.
Oh. isn't it?
Who else can soften Pharaoh's heart?
Or harden it?
Yes.
You may be the lovely dust
through which God
will work his purpose.
Fill every jar with water.
For seven days
there will be none to drink.
- But this well has never run dry.
- And the river is high.
- Whose word is that?
- One who knows.
So fill your jars or go thirsty.
- Miriam is always right.
- Yes. I'm going back for more jars.
Yes. Joshua.
She comes to the well every day.
Wait and you will see her.
It is wise of Dathan
to send you to the well. Lilia.
or he might find his water poisoned.
They told me you were dead.
To all I love. Joshua. I am dead.
- Dathan?
- Yes. Dathan.
Of your own free will?
Of my own free will.
You are no man's slave.
The hour of deliverance has come.
Not for me. Joshua.
Hail to thee. great god of the Nile!
Thy waters are the blood of Egypt.
Hail to thee. maker of barley.
feeder of cattle. carrier of ships.
greatest of all the gods.
Pharaoh of Egypt!
You have not yet obeyed the Lord.
Let my people go!
The point of the sword...
Let him rave
that men shall know him mad.
Obey the Lord
or he will raise his hand
against the waters of the river.
I have come to bless the waters.
you have come to curse them.
We will learn if a shepherd god
is stronger than the gods of Pharaoh.
Water of life.
give drink to the desert
and make green the meadow.
Aaron.
Stretch out my staff
against the waters.
Look!
Where he's touched the river.
it bleeds.
The water turns to blood!
(Woman screams)
Blood flows from the god!
See how it spreads.
It IS blood!
That you may know
the power of the Lord.
for seven days. Egypt will thirst.
- Seven days without water!
- Pestilence will be everywhere!
Were it seven times seven days.
no magician's trick
will set your people free.
Sacred water. make pure the flood
from which you came.
And God smote the land
with all manner of plagues.
but still Pharaoh's heart
was hardened.